A Guide to the Virginia Sexual and Domestic Violence Action Alliance records, 1972-2006
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Virginia Sexual and Domestic Violence Action Alliance records, 1972-2006
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 432
8.35 linear feet
Virginia Sexual and Domestic Violence Action Alliance
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Virginia Sexual and Domestic Violence Action Alliance in 2007.
Historical Information
The Virginia Sexual and Domestic Violence Action Alliance (VSDVAA) is a nonprofit agency committed to advocacy for victims of sexual and domestic abuse. Staff and volunteers collaborate with health professionals, law enforcement officers, and legislators, among other partners, in an effort to prevent and assist survivors of sexual and domestic violence. They produce a wide variety of publications, develop outreach programs, and provide training sessions to promote public awareness. Their goal is to prevent sexual and domestic violence by advancing social justice and providing individuals with the knowledge and tools to pursue healthy relationships.
The alliance was formed on October 1, 2004, when the nonprofit agencies Virginians Against Domestic Violence (VADV), founded in 1979 in Williamsburg, and Virginians Aligned Against Sexual Assault (VAASA), founded in 1980 in Charlottesville, joined together as a unified entity. The two organizations had worked together on various initiatives since the 1990s, including the VAdata Sexual and Domestic Violence Collection System created in 1996 and the Family Violence and Sexual Assault Hotline established in 1997. Their consolidation in 2004 was led by co-directors of VADV, Kristi Van Audenhove and Ruth Micklem, and the director of VAASA, Jeanine Bieber.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Sexual and Domestic Violence Alliance records primarily consist of materials generated and collected by its predecessor organization, VADV. These records document the VADV’s and VSDVAA’s day-to-day operations, public programs, and advocacy activities, and research on the issues of domestic and sexual violence and related topics.
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1981-2006. This series contains records created by VADV and VSDVAA that document the operational functions of the organizations. Materials include bylaws, mission statements, reports, plans, correspondence, financial documents, job descriptions, and materials documenting the organization's history.
Series 2: Project Files, 1985-2005. This series consists of materials generated by VADV and VSDVAA in the course of completing various projects, including creating and administering public programs and outreach activities. Materials found in this series include brochures, fact sheets, guides, newsletters, fliers, reports, notes, programs, and invitations.
Series 3: Reference Files, 1972-2005. The materials in this series consist of brochures, booklets, guides, reports, newsletters, articles, notes, and advertising materials collected by VADV and VSDVAA, many published by other agencies. These materials address domestic and sexual violence and a wide variety of related topics including emotional abuse, substance abuse, child care, available resources, legislation, victim's rights, household management, and personal finance.
Series 4: Press Files, 1979-2004. This series contains newspaper clippings of articles concerning domestic and sexual violence, particularly in Virginia, as well as a scrapbook of clippings, photographs, and other materials documenting the activities of VADV from 1979 to 1988. Also found in this series are a certificate and proclamation announcing observance of Domestic Violence Awareness Month in 1992 and 1998, respectively, and a program for the YWCA Outstanding Women Awards at which a member of the VADV board was recognized.
Series 5: Photographic Materials, circa 1983-2001. Materials in this series included photographic prints, negatives, and inkjet-printed photographs that document major events, conferences, training sessions, retreats, and special projects.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into five series: Series 1: Administrative Files, 1981-2006; Series 2: Project Files, 1985-2005; Series 3: Reference Files, 1972-2005; Series 4: Press Files, 1979-2004; and Series 5: Photographic Materials, circa 1983-2001.
Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Contents List
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 1981-2006
  - Ad Hoc Committee Reports and Meeting Minutes, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Annual Reports, 1993, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Board of Directors Legal Responsibilities and Statement of Understanding, undated (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Bylaws, Mission Statement, and Policy Statements, 1988-1989, undated (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1999, 2006, undated (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Financial Documents, 1981, 1994-2002 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Governor's Task Force on Coordinating Preventative Health, Education, and Social Program Meeting Agenda, 1986 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - History of Virginians Against Domestic Violence - Drafts and Timeline, 1985, 2001 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - History of VADV - Drafts and Timeline, 1985, 2001 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Job Descriptions, 1994-1995, undated (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Lobbyist Forms, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Logo and Branded Materials, 1985, undated (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Member Index Cards, 1985-1991, undated (Box 14)
  - Safe Deposit Box, 2003 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Solicitation Letters and Membership Information, 1988-1990, 1999, undated (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Strategic Plans and Informational Handout, 1995-2002 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Tax Exempt Status Files, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Series 2: Project Files, 1985-2005
  - Activist Toolkit and Desk Calendar, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Advocacy Day Coalition Resource Team Sketch Script and Props, 2000 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Advocate Newsletter, 2002 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Batterer Intervention Programs Fact Sheet, circa 1999 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Break the Silence Flier and Packet, circa 2003 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Calendar, 2001 (Drawer W1)
  - Christmas Cards, circa 1988 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Completed "Batterer's Treatment Programs" Surveys, 1995 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Domestic Violence and Services in Virginia Fact Sheet, 1998-2001 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Domestic Violence Awareness Month Invitations, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Domestic Violence Brochures, undated (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Emotional Abuse Brochures, 1998 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Family Violence and Sexual Assault Hotline - Ephemera, circa 1997 (Box 14)
  - Family Violence and Sexual Assault in Virginia Hotline - Information Sheets and Cards, circa 1997 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Gospel Sing Service Program, 1994 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - In Our Vision Newsletter, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Law Student Program - Administrative Notes and Training Materials, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Law Student Program - Administrative Notes and Training Materials, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Law Student Program - Handbook and Notes, 1986 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Lesbian Battering Brochure and Ad, undated (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Lesbian Battering Brochure and Ad, undated (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Lesbian Caucus of the Virginias Binder, 1995-1998 (Box-folder 2:16-2:17)
  - Lesbian Caucus Retreat Flier, undated (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Magistrates Training, 1989 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Marital Sexual Assault Brochure, undated (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Media Watch Map, 1998 (Box-folder 12:1)
  - Media Watch Report, 2002 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Resource Library Brochure, undated (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Safety Planning Brochures, undated (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Sexual Assault Brochure, undated (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Sexual Assault Survival Guide, undated (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Substance Abuse Brochures, undated (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Sunset on the James Benefit Invitation and Program, 1988 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Taking Action Newsletter, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Training Catalogs, 1999-2005 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Training Needs Assessment Form Report, undated (Box-folder 3:12)
  - VAdata Information Sheet and Reports, 2000-2001, undated (Box-folder 3:13)
  - VADV Lesbian Caucus, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 3:14-3:15)
  - Voter Registration Guide for Virginia Women, undated (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Worship Service Program with Domestic Violence Informational Insert, 1988 (Box-folder 3:17)
- Series 3: Reference Files, 1972-2005
  - Abuse Brochure, 1997 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Acquaintance Rape Packet, undated (Box-folder 3:19)
  - "Arrest in Domestic Violence Cases: A State by State Summary," 1987 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Child Care Materials, 1974-19827 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Childhood Materials, 1968-1979 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Communication Guides and Empathy Training Manual, 1974, undated (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Consciousness Raising Handout, 1976 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Consumer Affairs Materials, 1977-1979, undated (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Credit Materials, 1976-1981, undated (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Crime Prevention Materials, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Discrimination and Education Materials, 1973-1980, undated (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Discrimination and Employment Materials, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Domestic and Family Violence Materials, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Domestic Relations Rights in Virginia Brochure, 2002 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Domestic Violence Booklet, undated (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Domestic Violence Legal Process Guide, 2000 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Domestic Violence Safety Brochure, undated (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Drugs and Drug Abuse Materials, 1972, 1977 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Emergencies Materials, 1978, undated (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Emergency Housing for Battered Women and Their Children - Map, undated (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Energy Conservation Bibliography, circa 1980 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Family Abuse Protective Orders Chart, 2001 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Family and Intimate Partner Violence Homicide: Virginia 2000 - Report, 2002 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Family Violence Brochure, circa 1992 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Financial Assistance Materials, 1999-2000, undated (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Fundraising Materials, 1977-1985, undated (Box-folder 5:6)
  - "Hard Facts About Spouse Abuse," 1989 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - "Into the Light: A Guide for Battered Women," 1997 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Men Against Violence Against Women Packet, 1988 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - "Men Who Batter: A Resource Collection," circa 1984 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - National Coalition Against Domestic Violence Fact Sheet, circa 1994 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Response Newsletter - Assorted Topics, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Response Newsletter - Funding, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Response Newsletter - Legislation, 1979-1983, undated (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Response Newsletter - Shelters, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Sojourner, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 13:1-13:5)
  - Spousal Violence Against Women in Kentucky Report, 1979 (Box-folder 5:16)
  - "Stalking: A Guide for Victims," undated (Box-folder 5:17)
  - Stop Abuse Fliers, undated (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Sweet Honey in the Rock Brochure and Information Sheet, 1990 (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Vanity Fair containing "What Lisa Knew," 1988 (Box-folder 5:20)
  - "Violence and the Masculine Mystique," undated (Box-folder 5:21)
  - Virginia Family Violence Hotline Posters, undated (Box-folder 12:2)
  - Virginia Crime Victim and Witness Rights Act Brochures, 1997, 2000 (Box-folder 5:22)
  - Virginia Legislator Directory, 2005 (Box-folder 5:23)
  - "Will He Ever Change?: Treatment for Abusers," 1995 (Box-folder 5:24)
  - Women and Stress Workshop, circa 1980 (Box-folder 5:25)
  - Women's Organizations Directory, 1980 (Box-folder 5:26)
  - "Working with Abusers: A Resource Handbook," 1982 (Box-folder 5:27)
  - Working with Police, 1986 (Box-folder 5:28)
- Series 4: Press Files, 1979-2004
  - National Domestic Violence Awareness Month Proclamation, 1998 (Box-folder 13:5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1980-2004, undated (Box-folder 12:3-12:4)
  - Newspaper Sections - Richmond-Times Dispatch, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 13:6)
  - Newspaper Special Advertising Section - Virginia Family Violence and Sexual Assault Hotline, undated (Box-folder 13:7)
  - Scrapbook, 1979-1988 (Box-folder 12:5)
  - Scrapbook Duplicates, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 5:29)
  - Virginia Domestic Violence Awareness Month Certificate, 1992 (Box-folder 5:30)
  - YWCA Outstanding Women Awards Program, 2004 (Box-folder 5:31)
- Series 5: Photographic Materials, circa 1983-2001
  - Subseries A: Events, 1984-2001
    - Advancing Peace, Ensuring Justice Conference, 1995 (Box-folder 6:1)
    - Benefit Auction, 1985 (Box-folder 6:2)
    - Blue Light Campaign, Family and Children's Trust Fund, 1996 (Box-folder 6:3)
    - Clothesline Project, 1997 (Box-folder 6:4)
    - Conference, circa 1995 (Box-folder 6:5)
    - Conference at the Jefferson in Richmond, Virginia, 1993 (Box-folder 6:6)
    - Conference on Spouse Abuse, circa 1984 (Box-folder 6:7)
    - Conference with Governor Chuck Robb, 1985 (Box-folder 6:8)
    - Domestic Violence Awareness Month Proclamation Signing, 1989 (Box-folder 6:9)
    - Domestic Violence Awareness Month Proclamation Signing with Governor L. Douglas Wilder, 1992 (Box-folder 6:10)
    - Gospel Sing by Women of Color Caucus, circa 1990s (Box-folder 6:11)
    - Hotline Mall Display, circa 1990s (Box-folder 6:12)
    - Hotline Opening, 1997 (Box-folder 6:13)
    - K-mart Event, circa 1990s (Box-folder 6:14)
    - Musical Performance with Candace Feathers, 1992 (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Musicians for "Voices of Freedom" Fundraiser, 1994 (Box-folder 6:16)
    - National Coalition Against Domestic Violence, 1994 (Box-folder 6:17)
    - Office Holiday Party, 1995 (Box-folder 6:18)
    - Office Holiday Party, 2001 (Box-folder 7:1)
    - Peace Awards, 2000 (Box-folder 7:2)
    - Peace Awards, 2001 (Box-folder 7:3)
    - Project Hope, circa 1990s (Box-folder 7:4)
    - Statewide Domestic Violence Memorial Service, 1987 (Box-folder 7:5)
    - Stop Violence Against Women, Hillary Clinton Visit, 2000 (Box-folder 7:6)
    - Washington, D.C. Trip, 1995 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Subseries B: People, circa 1983-2001
    - Board Members, circa 1999 (Box-folder 7:8)
    - Hien, Patricia, 1993 (Box-folder 7:9)
    - Hien, Patricia and Robin Thomas, 1990 (Box-folder 7:10)
    - Lamm, Cindy, undated (Box-folder 7:11)
    - Micklem, Ruth and Debra Simmons, 1990 (Box-folder 7:12)
    - Office Staff, 2000 (Box-folder 7:13)
    - Office Staff, 2001 (Box-folder 7:14)
    - Reuss, Pat, circa 1990s (Box-folder 7:15)
    - Staff, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Staff Member - Monica, 2000 (Box-folder 8:2)
    - Steinem, Gloria, circa 1983 (Box-folder 8:3)
    - Van Audenhove, Kristi, 1993 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Subseries C: Retreats and Training, 1986-2001
    - Culture and International Domestic Violence Awareness Training in Alexandria, Virginia, 2001 (Box-folder 8:5)
    - Finding Time Folds Training Retreat at Radford University, 1995 (Box-folder 8:6)
    - Men Stopping Violence: Building Bridges Training, 2000 (Box-folder 8:7)
    - Planet Fun VADV / VAASA Retreat and Advanced Training, 2001 (Box-folder 8:8)
    - Retreat, 1986 (Box-folder 8:9)
    - Retreat, 1989 (Box-folder 8:10)
    - Retreat, circa 1990s (Box-folder 8:11)
    - Retreat, 1999 (Box-folder 8:12)
    - Retreat for VADV / VAASA, 2000 (Box-folder 9:1)
    - Retreat for VADV / VAASA at Hampton University, 1996 (Box-folder 9:2)
    - Retreat for VADV / VAASA at Smith Mountain Lake, Virginia, 1998 (Box-folder 9:3)
    - Retreat for VADV / VAASA in Appomattox, Virginia, 1994 (Box-folder 9:4)
    - Retreat for VADV in Front Royal, Virginia, 1997 (Box-folder 10:1)
    - Retreat in Wakefield, Virginia, 1993 (Box-folder 10:2)
    - Retreat Musicians, 1995 (Box-folder 10:3)
    - Staff Retreat at Camp Chance, circa 1990s (Box-folder 10:4)
    - Training, 2000 (Box-folder 10:5)
    - Training for Social Change, 2001 (Box-folder 10:6)
    - Training for Trainers, 1996 (Box-folder 10:7)
    - Training for Trainers, 1997 (Box-folder 10:8)
    - Training for Trainers, 1998 (Box-folder 10:9)
    - Training for Trainers, 1999 (Box-folder 10:10)
    - Training for Trainers and Advanced Training for Trainers, 2001 (Box-folder 11:1)
    - Training Session in Wimby, Virginia with Ellen Pence and Others, 1997 (Box-folder 11:2)
  - Subseries D: Miscellaneous, 1986-1999
    - Flier for VADV, undated (Box-folder 11:3)
    - House Photographs for Membership Brochure, circa 1990s (Box-folder 11:4)
    - Unidentified Ink Jet Prints, undated (Box-folder 5:32)
    - Unidentified Negatives, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 11:5)
    - Unidentified Photographs, 1986-1988, undated (Box-folder 11:6)
    - Unidentified Photographs of Animals, 1986, 1989 (Box-folder 11:7)
    - Virginia General Assembly Photographs for VADV Newsletter Courtesy of Project Horizon, 1991 (Box-folder 11:8)